A Guide to the Martin P. Chworsky Collection 1948-1967
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Martin P. Chworsky Collection 1948-1967
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 10
18 linear feet
Martin P. Chworsky
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to the Department in February 1974 and January 1976 by Mrs. Martin P. Chworsky.
Biographical/Historical Information
Martin Philip Chworsky was born on 28 January 1900, in San Antonio, Texas. In 1922, he matriculated from Harvard, spending the next four years at the Harvard Law School. He received his LLB in 1926 but never practiced law. He began his teaching career in a Connecticut secondary school and remained in the field of education for the rest of his life. He became a lecturer in education at the University of Pittsburgh in 1931. While at the University of Pittsburgh he earned his Master's degree in 1934 and his Ph.D. in 1936.
From 1939 to 1946, Dr Chworsky was an associate professor of psychology and education at the Carnegie Institute of Technology. He left this post to work for two years as the associate director of the Commission on Educational Organization of the National Conference of Christians and Jews.
At Teachers College, Columbia University, Dr Chworsky was coordinator of that college's program in Intergroup Education from 1948 to 1951.
The newly founded Albert M. Greenfield Center for Human Relations chose him as its first director and he remained in this post until the dissolution of the Center. Following this, he joined the Sociology Department at Virginia Commonwealth University. He retired from VCU in 1970 and died 29 April 1975.
Scope and Content Information
The Martin P Chworsky collection consists of excerpted articles in the area of human relations by various authors, certain of Dr Chworsky's writings and lecture notes, and miscellaneous data and correspondence related to his years as director of the Albert M. Greenfield Center for Human Relations at the University of Pennsylvania. All materials are basically from the period 1957-1964 which coincides with his major period of publishing activity, 1955-1966.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Materials are arranged by title or subject and chronological therein
Organization
The materials in these two collections have been arranged alphabetically by title or subject matter. If possible, they have been further arranged in chronological order. There is one exception. Collection 10- a contains the majority of materials relating to the Albert M. Greenfield Center for Human Relations, and all materials in collection 10 relating to theis subject have been moved to 10-a for convenience.
Other Descriptive Data
Additonal articles and other materials can be found in the file cabinets in the old stack area. The files are arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
Contents List
- American Conscience, (Burlingame) excerpts 1957 (Box 1)
- Bibliographies, Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 1)
- Bridgeview Study on Fair Housing(nearprint) n.d. (Box 1)
- Chruch and State in the United States(Stokes) excerpts n.d. (Box 1)
- Church/State relations, excerpted articles on n.d. (Box 1)
- Church/State relations 1961 (Box 1)
- Church/State relations 1962 (Box 1)
- Church/State relations 1963 (Box 1)
- Church/State relations 1964 (Box 1)
- Church/State relations 1965 (Box 2)
- Church & State (Folder 1) n.d. (Box 2)
- Church & State (Folder 2) n.d. (Box 2)
- Class & Lecture Materials n.d. (Box 2)
- Clippings n.d. (Box 2)
- Constitutional Right of Association, excerpts n.d. (Box 2)
- Correspondence n.d. (Box 2)
- Cultural Values of American Ethnic Groups(Woods), excerpts 1956 (Box 2)
- Desegregation, excerpted articles on n.d. (Box 2)
- Education, miscellaneous articles n.d. (Box 2)
- Education in Depressed Areas(Passow), excerpts n.d. (Box 2)
- Education in Depressed Areas(Passow) n.d. (Box 3)
- Fair Housing, articles on n.d. (Box 3)
- Great Transformation, The(Polanyi), excerpts 1951 (Box 3)
- Group Relations, articles on n.d. (Box 3)
- Human Relations, galley of article n.d. (Box 3)
- Idea of Nationalism, The (Kohn), excerpts 1948 (Box 3)
- Intergroup Relationships, carbon n.d. (Box 3)
- Interracial Review, articles from 1954 1954 (Box 3)
- Internal Security, articles n.d. (Box 3)
- Jews and Anti-Semitism, articles on n.d. (Box 3)
- Laissez Faire and the General Welfare State(Fine), excerpts 1956 (Box 3)
- Legal Rights n.d. (Box 3)
- Man in Modern Age(Jaspers) n.d. (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 3)
- Nature of Prejudice(Allport) n.d. (Box 4)
- Non-Violent Resistence, articles n.d. (Box 4)
- Non-Violent Resistence, articles 1960 (Box 4)
- Non-Violent Resistence, articles 1963 (Box 4)
- Organization of Social Welfare Policy(near print) 1967 (Box 4)
- Outline of Social Psychology(Sherif), excerpts n.d. (Box 4)
- Outlines on Phenomenology n.d. (Box 4)
- Phenomenological Approach to Human Relations(folder 1) n.d. (Box 4)
- Phenomenological Approach to Human Relations(folder 2) n.d. (Box 4)
- Police Training(near print) 1968 (Box 4)
- Political Liberty(A.J. Carlyle), excerpts 1963 (Box 4)
- Political Dynamics (carbon) n.d. (Box 4)
- Profile of the Negro American, A(Pettigrew) 1964 (Box 5)
- Poverty and Labor, articles 1964 (Box 5)
- Religion, articles 1963 (Box 5)
- Sample Study: A Technique for Social Science Reference n.d. (Box 5)
- Sapir, Edward, articles n.d. (Box 5)
- Schelsinger, Arthur, excerpts n.d. (Box 5)
- Social Research(vol. 29) excerpts n.d. (Box 5)
- Sociology of Knowledge(Stark) 1956 (Box 5)
- Segregation and Catholic Schools(near print) n.d. (Box 5)
- Social Groups (folder 1) n.d. (Box 5)
- Social Groups (folder 2) n.d. (Box 5)
- Social Strat. in US(Cuber & Kendall) excerpts (Box 5)
- Social Psychology(Newcomb) excerpts (Box 5)
- Functions of Social Conflict(Coser) excerpts n.d. (Box 5)
- The Sociological Mechanisms of Non-Violent Action(near print) 1962 (Box 5)
- Speeches & Lectures n.d. (Box 5)
- A Theory of Migration(near print) 1950 (Box 5)
- Speeches by others n.d. (Box 5)
- Student papers on Non-violent Resistance n.d. (Box 5)
- Greenfield Center n.d. (Box 5)
- Correspondence, Misc. (Albert M. Greenfield) 1953-1965 (Box 5)
- Center for Human Relations, 33 items (Box 5)
- Albert M. Greenfield Center for Human Relations, msicellaneous data n.d., 25 items (Box 5)
- Lecture Outlines n.d. (Box 5)